All right.
בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, today we are in קידושין דף כח
Kiddushin Daf Chaf-Chet and we pick up at the bottom of כז
עמוד ב Chaf-Zayin Amud Bet
and we are dealing with the issue about גלגול שבועה. gilgul shvua.
We're wrapping up the end of a משנה mishna that spoke about
this קנין על קרקע kinyan al karka and through קרקע, karka, good
morning, how קרקע karka you could be קונה מטלטלין koneh metaltelin with
a קנין אגב. kinyan agav. If you do the קנין kinyan on
the קרקע karka then it also works for for chattel, whether the
chattel's on the land, not on the land, that was discussed. And
now we're dealing with the reverse sort of connection, that you could
take a שבועה shvua on מטלטלין metaltelin and once you get somebody
to take a שבועה shvua on מטלטלין metaltelin you can force him
to take a שבועה shvua on קרקע karka as well, that's גלגול
שבועה, gilgul shvua, even though קרקע karka is categorically excluded, you can
force him to take a שבועה shvua once you get him to
take a שבועה shvua on מטלטלין. metaltelin. And we learned that out
from סוטה Sotah because by סוטה, Sotah, אמן אמן, Amen Amen, if
a woman is forced by the פרשת סוטה parshat Sotah to take
an oath that she didn't have sex with a certain man in
terms of adultery, then you can force an oath even for a
case that never could have been a סוטה Sotah case, a case
where the woman was an ארוסה. arusa. So that shows you the
principle of גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua and you could apply it even
to cases that are categorically excluded. Okay, and then the גמרא Gemara
said because of a קל וחומר kal vachomer we can apply it
even to if we can make the apply this principle of גלגול
שבועה gilgul shvua from a case of איסור, issur, from a case
of a שבועה shvua about adultery, to a case of ממון, mamon,
to a case of a שבועה shvua relating to monetary matters. So
now we pick up with that on the top of כח עמוד
א Chaf-Chet Amud Aleph and two lines, three lines from the top,
beginning of the line, אשכחן בודאי. Ashk'chan be-vada'i. Now we know that
this can be in a case where it is definite. Now what
is definite?
So רש"י Rashi says that like for example
let's say for example you have a question about a meaning the
second claim is a definite claim as opposed to, let's read the
גמרא, Gemara, I'm sorry, let's read the field. אשכחן בודאי, Ashk'chan be-vada'i,
we found this in a case of ודאי, vadai, ספק מנלן, safa-me-nalan,
where do you know by ספק? safek? We'll read the גמרא, Gemara,
the גמרא Gemara will make it clear. תניא רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי אומר נאמר שבועה בחוץ ונאמר שבועה בפנים. Tanya Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai omer Ne'emar shvua ba-chutz ve-ne'emar shvua bifnim. It says a
שבועה shvua outside, okay, so you know by the by a שבועה
shvua in a בית דין, Beit Din, and it says a שבועה
shvua inside, meaning in a case by the סוטה, Sotah, which is
inside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. מה שבועה בפנים עשה בו ספק
כודאי, Ma shvua bifnim asa bo safek ke-vadai, by a שבועה shvua
on the inside, the ספק safek is like a ודאי, vadai, meaning
the claim that the husband is making is he doesn't know for
sure, right, he's just suspecting, and nevertheless can force a שבועה. shvua.
אף שבועה בחוץ עשה בו ספק כודאי, Af shvua ba-chutz asa bo
safek ke-vadai, so even on the outside, a שבועה shvua about ממון
mamon in a בית דין, Beit Din, you can do it even
in a case of a doubt, which means, right, that there are
a שבועה, shvua, let's say I say that I suspect you of
something, right, a normal case of a שבועה shvua that you make
is a case where there's a טענת ברי. ta'anat bari. I say,
you know, that you borrowed a hundred dollars, you say you didn't,
and then there's an עד אחד ed echad that says you did,
okay, so I have a טענת ברי, ta'anat bari, or I say
you borrowed a hundred and you say I paid you back fifty,
no, I only borrowed fifty, so I have a טענת ברי. ta'anat
bari. But ספק? safek? That's, well, it's a ספק safek to the
בית דין, Beit Din, it's a ברי bari to me. My claim
is definite, right?
מודה במקצת, Modeh be-miktzat, oh, I see what you say.
Okay, I'm making a claim that I definitely know and that you're
lying. The case by the סוטה Sotah was that the husband was
making the claim that he doesn't know and he's forcing a שבועה.
shvua. So the question is, how do you know you can do
a גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua from a case where it maybe started
with a שבועה shvua that you can really obligate, okay, like a
שבועת מודה במקצת shvuat modeh be-miktzat or whatever, טענת ברי, ta'anat bari,
but now I'm saying now that I'm getting you to make a
שבועה, shvua, you know, I have a lot of things I have
suspicions about, okay, and I'm going to make you take a שבועה
shvua about all these things I've been suspecting you about recently. That's
a ספק, safek, I suspect you about these things, I don't know
for sure, okay? But I'm
definitely suspicious. So how do you know you can do that? So
you learn that from גלגול שבועה, gilgul shvua, from סוטה. Sotah. The
same way סוטה Sotah you can take the take a שבועה shvua
about ספק, safek, by a גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua you can also
take a שבועה shvua about ספק. safek. Okay? So let's take a
look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, עד היכן גלגול שבועה. Ad
heichan gilgul shvua. Now how far does the גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua
go, meaning to what extent, now from the context it sounds like
it's saying what type of crazy suspicion would you still be able
to make the guy take a שבועה shvua about? All right, but
we'll see how the גמרא Gemara interprets it. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב דאמר ליה השבע לי שאין עבדי אתה. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav de-amar leh hishava li she-ein avdi ata. Swear to me that
you're not my slave. Okay, so the way I would normally read
this in in sort of juxtaposition of the previous סוגיא sugya is
like, I suspect you of everything under the sun, you know, and
you know, who knows, like maybe even you were, you know, you
were my father's slave and he didn't tell me, swear to me
about even this crazy possibility that you're not my slave. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara doesn't understand it that way. Let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara reads it.
So it basically started off with some simple questions they knew the
answers to.
Very good. Right. And then they go to others. So the גמרא
Gemara says ההוא דשמתיה משמתינן ליה. hahu deshameiteih mishamteinan lei.
What? The very fact that you're claiming that he is or he
might be a slave, we put you in חרם, cherem, in נידוי.
nidduy. דתניא, detanya, taught in a ברייתא, braita, הקורא לחברו עבד, hakorei
lachaveiro eved, if you call your friend a slave, יהא בנידוי, yehei
benidduy, you're put in נידוי. nidduy. ממזר, mamzer, if you call him
a ממזר, mamzer, סופג את הארבעים, sofeg et ha'arbaim, you get forty
lashes. רשע, rasha, if you call him a wicked person, יורד עמו
לחייו, yored immo lechayav, then we basically let the person you know
compete with you in business in a way that we otherwise wouldn't
have. Now what is all of that about by the way before
we get to applying that to our case? Why the different types
of punishments for the different things? So תוספות Tosafot has a very
nice explanation. תוספות Tosafot says like this. He says
three lines down in the wide lines of תוספות, Tosafot, the תוספות
הקורא לחברו, Tosafot hakorei lachaveiro, but if you go three lines down,
תוספות Tosafot says והיינו מידה כנגד מידה, ve-hainu mida k'neged mida, כלומר,
klomar, הוא קרא לחברו עבד, hu kara lachaveiro eved,
you called him a slave, דהוי ארור, dahavei arur, because עבדים avadim
are you know ארור כנען, arur Kena'an, כך מנדין אותו בארור, kach
menadin oto be'arur, you curse him because you put him in נידוי
nidduy which is a type of a curse, right? I mean it
has practical implications but it's also an act of censure and cursing,
דהיינו נידוי. de-hainu nidduy. Okay, so that's why the נידוי nidduy is
for calling your friend a slave. וכן הקורא לחברו ממזר, ve-chen hakorei
lachaveiro mamzer, so הוא אומר שחברו עבר בלאו. hu omer she-chaveiro avar
belav.
He says his friend did a לאו, lav, presumably because maybe he
was a ממזר mamzer married to somebody else. Okay, so but or
maybe he was suggesting that the parents did an איסור issur obviously
to make a ממזר. mamzer. לפיכך סופג את הארבעים, le-fichach sofeg et
ha'arbaim, כדין עובר בלאו. kedin over belav. So if you claim that
he was being עובר over on something, you're going to get lashes
as if you were עובר over on something. And presumably the same
is by the last thing. You called him a רשע, rasha, so
a רשע rasha is somebody that like
improperly you know
affects somebody's like a רשע rasha could be often things related to
money and you know and hurting somebody monetarily and so on. Therefore
you get hurt monetarily and we allow this person to even like
compete with you in business in ways we otherwise wouldn't have allowed.
Yes.
Didn't we learn in a previous מסכת masechet a סוגיא sugya that
there's a difference between שמותי shamtei and נידוי? nidduy? And here it
says it's more general.
Well no, there's a difference between נידוי nidduy and חרם. cherem.
שמותי shamtei means נידוי. nidduy. Yeah. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so how could you even suggest that he's an עבד? eved?
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, no, השבע לי שלא נמכרת לי בעבד
עברי. hishava li she-lo nimkarta li be-eved Ivri.
Swear to me that you weren't sold to me as an עבד
עברי. eved Ivri. Now what is the shift between that and swear
to me you're not my slave? So רש"י Rashi says that the
shift is when you say עבדי אתה, avdi ata, it means you're
an עבד כנעני. eved Kena'ani. Right. And that's what תוספות Tosafot suggest
too because he said בארור. be'arur. So first I'm saying you're my
slave, meaning I'm claiming that a Jew is not a Jew, he's
an עבד כנעני. eved Kena'ani. So that's obviously something that you know
you can't go ahead and do and we wouldn't even we wouldn't
tolerate that for a second. Okay, if you want to say he's
an עבד עברי, eved Ivri, that's like a different discussion. Okay,
so although I wonder and maybe I'm being a little bit
too contemporary about this, but I wonder if the difference is not
just עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani and עבד עברי eved Ivri but about
whether you're doing it as a personal label or not. One case
said you're a slave. The other case said I'm not whatever, I'm
saying you you were you know you you were sold to me
as an עבד עברי. eved Ivri. I'm not directly attaching the label
to you. I'm not labeling you. Okay, so you know it's like
we talk about like you know a person with this issue as
opposed to use calling using the label to label the person. So
anyway there is interest that there is that shift, right? It didn't
say השבע לי שאינך hishava li she-eincha you know that you're not
my עבד עברי. eved Ivri. We switched it from a label to
that you weren't sold to me in the capacity of an עבד
עברי. eved Ivri. So I might be a little overreading that, but
it is worth noting that shift as well. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, so then why is that a חידוש? chiddush? הא
טענת ממון היא? ha ta'anat mamon hi? That's a normal
טענה ta'ana ממונית. mamonit. You're saying you owed me money and you're
being you're now my עבד עברי eved Ivri to pay off that
money. So why is that different than any other claim? So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, רבא לטעמיה, Rava l'ta'ameih, רבא Rava is going
by his reasoning, דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava, עבד עברי גופו קנוי. eved
Ivri gufo kanuy.
An עבד עברי eved Ivri there's a sense of a קניין. kinyan.
So therefore I'm saying swear to me that you're not my עבד
עברי, eved Ivri, so I basically claim that I own a piece
of you. Okay, but why is that a חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש
chiddush is because if you own a piece of a person, so
we know that עבדים avadim are like קרקע karka and you don't
take a שבועה shvu'ah on קרקע karka and you don't take a
שבועה shvu'ah on עבדים. avadim. So if I'm saying I own a
piece of you, swear to me that I don't, that's a שבועה
shvu'ah technically on קרקע, karka, on an ownership of property or persons
because according to רבא Rava the עבד עברי eved Ivri is גופו
קנוי gufo kanuy and you don't make a שבועה shvu'ah on it.
So the חידוש chiddush is because by גלגול שבועה, gilgul shvu'ah, the
same way you can make a שבועה shvu'ah on קרקע, karka, you
can make a שבועה shvu'ah on issues about relating to slaves, ownerships
of people. But what's the חידוש? chiddush? It's the same as קרקע.
karka. Very funny, right? That a person, you can't have something that's
a bigger piece of מטלטלין metaltelin than a human being, right?
Yeah, but we talked about how that has to do with the
fact that קרקע karka to some degree... is not fully owned in
the same or under control in the same way people are not.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי היינו קרקע, ei hachi hainu
karka, so what's still, what's the חידוש? chidush? So that's an issue
about a שבועה shvuah about ownership of a person is like ownership
of land, and we know you could do a גלגול שבועה gilgul
shvuah on קרקע. karka. Now מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might have
thought קרקע הוא דעבדי אינשי דמזבני בצינעא, karka hu de-avdi inshi de-mizbeni
be-tzina, קרקע karka people sometimes sell in private, ואיכא דזבין ליה דלא
קלא, ve-ika dezavin lei delo kala, and it's possible that it was
sold and that nobody knows about it. So therefore it's a reasonable
claim and you can make a שבועה shvuah by base on גלגול
שבועה, gilgul shvuah, that maybe this is my property, you know, this
is my property and you're lying to me. אבל האי אם איתא
דזבין קלא אית ליה, aval hai im ita dezavin kala it lei,
but I would say it's not a reasonable claim that he's your
עבד עברי, eved ivri, everybody would have known if he was your
עבד עברי. eved ivri. So we don't even tolerate the claim and
therefore and therefore we shouldn't accept it. קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that we do. So it's interesting that the גמרא's Gemara shift
in the end, because as soon as it said, swear me you're
not my slave, the initial reaction I would have is like even
an absurd claim. So the גמרא, Gemara, you know, that you can
make, to force somebody to make even on an absurd claim. So
the גמרא Gemara digressed to discuss, well not digressed anyway, but discussed
like, well, if it's just a קרקע karka issue, what's the חידוש?
chidush? It's so what, it's category, it's not different than the way
קרקע's karka excluded. But in the end the conclusion was that that
was the חידוש. chidush. The חידוש chidush was that even though it
seems far-fetched that this person would be an עבד עברי, eved ivri,
because A, maybe it's not so common we have עבדי עברי, avdei
ivri, B, if there is an עבד עברי, eved ivri, we know
about it. So even though the claim seems far-fetched, you can still
make the person take that שבועה shvuah based on גלגול שבועה. gilgul
shvuah. So גלגול שבועה gilgul shvuah you can take on something categorically
excluded, קרקע karka and עבדים, avadim, and even on a claim of
a ספק, safek, and even a claim that is relatively far-fetched. So
the people have like said like, you know, English words that sound
like Yiddish ones, far-fetched has got to be the best. It's so
far-fetched.
Anyway, okay so, the question is, how how how like completely out
of the, you know, just speculative could the שבועה shvuah be? So
if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot tries to rein it
in a little bit. תוספות Tosafot says נאמר שבועה בפנים. ne'emar shvuah
bifnim. תוספות Tosafot says the following, תוספות Tosafot says,
ואומר רבי, vaomer rebbi, it's about six lines before that תוספות Tosafot
נאמר ne'emar finishes. The line starts with the word כודאי. kevadai. See
that? So תוספות Tosafot says ואומר רבי שלא כל ספק מגלגלין, vaomer
rebbi shelo kol safek megalgelin,
not on every type of a question, you know, a speculation, שאם
נתחייב אדם לחברו שבועה, she-im nitchayev adam le-chavero shvuah, if you owe
me a שבועה shvuah
for a particular reason, אם יוכל לגלגל ולומר השבע לי שלא גנבת
לי שום דבר מעולם, im yuchal legalgel velomar hishaveh li shelo ganavta
li shum davar me-olam, swear to me that you've never done, you
know, you never did anything wrong to me, that you never stole
anything from me, you never borrowed any money from me, like סתם.
stam. You can't just, you know, speculate out of thin air. אלא
דוקא בספק שיש לנו לחוש קצת, ela davka besafek she-yesh lanu lachush
k-tzat,
only something that has a little basis for being concerned about, כגון
נעשה לו שותף או אריס, kegon na'asa lo shutaf o aris, let's
say we were partners, and then after we broke up the partnership
I want you to swear that you never misappropriated any funds. So
okay, there's a basis for that. We're partners, you and we were
handling each other's money, you know, there's a reason to think that
maybe you did that. וכי האי גוונא אמרינן בסוף כל הנשבעים דמגלגלין.
ve-chi hai gavna amrinan besof kol hanishba'im demegalgelin. So the question though
is, you know, how do you how do you square that with
the גמרא Gemara about swear to me that you're not my עבד
עברי, eved ivri, right? So, you know, that also seems very far-fetched
and there's no basis to assume that this person, like would we
need the fact that maybe, you know, it's clear that I'm rich
and you're poor and it's reasonable to assume that you might have
borrowed money from me, etc.? Or like, you know, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't put it in that context. So anyway תוספות Tosafot is pulling
back a little bit from the extreme of the גמרא Gemara because
really like, you know, how would anybody allow themselves to take a
שבועה? shvuah? You could make them swear anything under the sun, any
ספק safek on anything, right? It's it could be a טענת ספק,
ta'anat safek, it could be something very far-fetched, it could be on
קרקע, karka, it could be on anything. So תוספות Tosafot tries to
pull back a little from the גמרא Gemara and says that there
has to be at least a little bit of a basis for
suspicion.
But the קא משמע לן ka mashma lan of the סוגיא sugya
is we do, we do require this שבועה shvuah by עבד עברי.
eved ivri. So that's why תוספות Tosafot pulls back from that. Right.
I mean, yes, that's what the גמרא Gemara sounds like, but תוספות
Tosafot pulls back a little bit or else it would really be
like out of, you know, absurd. Alright, so now we go on
to the next משנה. mishnah. So that was a little digression to
גלגול שבועה, gilgul shvuah, which and and now we turn back to
the next because of the relationship of קרקע karka to מטלטלין. metaltelin.
So the next משנה: mishnah: כל הנעשה דמים באחר. kol hana'aseh damim
be-acher. Now this משנה mishnah is very challenging, not so much conceptually,
but because the words it, it just uses complicated phrasing and complicated
words and the גמרא Gemara tries to figure out what the basic
points of reference of this משנה mishnah are. And it seems also
that this is probably a more archaic and an older משנה mishnah
and therefore uses a different type of terminology. So כל הנעשה דמים
באחר, kol hana'aseh damim be-acher, so we're still within קניינים, kinyanim, anything
that would become money relating to something else, I'll just translate it
literally, anything that would be money relating to something else, כיון שזכה
זה. kevan she-zacha zeh. Once this one takes possession, נתחייב זה בחליפיו,
nitchayav zeh bechalifav, the other one is obligated in the exchange. Well,
that was clear enough. Okay. So now, the next line is very
clear. כיצד, keitzad, החליף שור בפרה, hechlif shor befarah, if we're exchanging
an ox with a cow, so או חמור בשור, o chamor beshor,
or a donkey with an ox,
so a... wait, חמור chamor is a mule, right?
חמור chamor is a mule, right? A donkey is... what's a donkey?
A donkey is something else. A... right, חמור chamor is a mule.
Right, a mule with an ox. כיון שזכה זה, keivan shezachah zeh,
נתחייב זה בחליפיו. nitchayav zeh bechalifav. Once this one takes possession, the
other one is obligated in the exchange. So the עניין inyan seems
to be a simple issue of barter. Right, ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon are exchanging animals, you know, your mule for your cow. Okay.
Once ראובן Reuven takes the mule, the other one שמעון Shimon is
obligated now to give him the... now wait, that doesn't work, right?
Because it's not שמעון Shimon is now obligated to give him the
exchange, it's now, right, that's part of the... even here the language
is funny. You wanted to say once ראובן Reuven takes the mule,
ראובן Reuven is now obligated to give him. So the נתחייב זה,
nitchayav zeh, תוספות Tosafot has a question what the גרסה girsa is.
There might not be the second זה. zeh. If there wasn't the
second זה zeh it would be easier. כיון שזכה זה, נתחייב בחליפיו.
keivan she-zachah zeh nitchayav b'chalifav. Once you take possession, you're obligated to
give the exchange. So if you have the... right?
No, the second
זה zeh refers to the other guy.
You bring a cow, I bring a donkey. Yeah. You take my
donkey away and I haven't taken your cow yet, it's still my
cow, you're responsible for it.
Ah, so that's the question of what נתחייב nitchayav is. Okay. So
here we've got the donkey, I'm not even going to try to
draw the difference between a donkey and a cow. Okay. Here we've
got the donkey. So שמעון, Shimon, זכה זה, zachah zeh, he takes
the donkey. So this is זכה זה, zachah zeh, that's שמעון, Shimon,
זכה זה. zachah zeh. Now, then we say once he takes the
donkey, נתחייב זה, nitchayav zeh, the introduction of the other word זה
zeh seems to mean that we're pointing to the other guy. I
just want to point out that תוספות Tosafot has a גרסה girsa
that doesn't have the נתחייב זה. nitchayav zeh. It says כיון שזכה
זה, keivan shezachah zeh, נתחייב, nitchayav, נתחייב בחליפיו. nitchayav bechalifav. If
that was your גרסה, girsa, it means once you took it, you're
obligated to give the exchange. That's one way. But the way of
reading of נתחייב זה בחליפיו nitchayav zeh bechalifav
is, Jonathan, what you're saying, you're saying נתחייב זה בחליפיו nitchayav zeh
bechalifav is saying that once שמעון Shimon has it, ראובן Reuven is
obligated in any loss that happens to the cow. It's his cow,
and even though it remains in שמעון's Shimon's possession, it's now his
cow and any loss would be at ראובן's Reuven's expense and not
at שמעון's Shimon's expense. So that's the other way of reading it.
Okay. So נתחייב nitchayav doesn't mean to give the חליפין, chalifin, it
essentially means you're זוכה בחליפיו, zocheh bechalifav, you become owning this object
and therefore you are responsible for any loss.
Okay. In other words, in other words,
ראובן Reuven gives the donkey, and then like שמעון Shimon calls him
up two days later like "When you gonna come take the cow?"
"Right, I'm busy." Right. So שמעון Shimon said "Well listen, if anything
happens it's your cow, it's in my backyard. If it trips over
the lawnmower, don't blame me."
Exactly. Okay. So that's the עניין. inyan. So that's clear. But the
problem is, so now we know what זכה זה נתחייב זה zachah
zeh nitchayav zeh means, but the problem is, okay, whether you have
the second זה zeh or not. But the problem is, what does
this first phrase of כל הנעשה דמים באחר kol hana'aseh damim be'acher
mean? Anything that's money relating to something else, like what? What are
you talking about? Like, you know,
is it מטלטלין? metaltelin? What are you trying to say? Okay, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara tries to figure out. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Would this historically be that the סיפא seifa is later?
That's what I think.
To explicate. That's what I think. I think that the רישא reisha
was said in this very archaic language and it's not at all
clear what it means and the סיפא seifa makes it much clearer
that we're talking about exchanging two objects. Okay, this is a קניין
חליפין kinyan chalifin by the way. Let's just label it. We've been
talking about it for a long time, but this is the קניין
kinyan of חליפין chalifin of exchange. And the other thing I need
to say, which is going to be very relevant in appreciating the
גמרא, Gemara, is that there are two forms of חליפין chalifin which
I would say logically should be categorized as completely different. Okay, there's
one form of חליפין chalifin which is what the end of the
משנה Mishnah talks about, which is barter. You know, I take one
object, you get the exchange object. There's another form of חליפין chalifin
which is sort of the handkerchief form, which is קניין סודר, kinyan
sudar, which is sort of modeled after it, but that's not really
exchange. Like you take the handkerchief and you become obligated in the
terms of a contract. Like we're not exchanging a handkerchief for the
terms of the contract, right? It's more that the... that it's a
signal of my גמירות דעת gemirut da'at that I'm committing to it.
It's a formal act of commitment, and therefore I can obligate myself
in financial obligations, terms of a contract, I can also transfer an
object through that, but it comes through more this as an act
that signifies my גמירות דעת. gemirut da'at. Now, one way that you
see that these are really very, very different is, well, first is
some of the special הלכות halachot of קניין סודר. kinyan sudar. First
of all, by קניין סודר... kinyan sudar... you don't even have to
let go of the object. Anybody ever see like when the rabbi
and the חתן *Chosson* hold it up at the same time? You
give the object a מתנה על מנת להחזיר *Matana Al
Menas Lehachzir* and whatever the object has to go back. And so,
like, it would be—I'm not saying you can't have that by a
barter, but it would be very hard to imagine all of that
by a barter. Here, I'm giving you take possession of half of
my donkey, and I'm holding on to the other half, and you're
going to have to give it back to me after you're done,
and through this I'm going to get your cow. Right? Like, huh?
So anyway, that's already things that are very different. But the more
most extreme points of difference is with there's a debate in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about whether קנין סודר kinyan sudar. *Kinyan Sudar* works
בכלי של קונה koneh *B'keli Shel Koneh* or בכלי של מקנה *B'keli
Shel Makneh*. So what I mean is, is that I am, let's
say it's really I'm going to just sell, give you my car
with a קנין kinyan חליפין chalipin, *Kinyan Chalupin*, okay? With a קנין
סודר kinyan sudar *Kinyan Sudar*, קנין kinyan חליפין chalipin. *Kinyan Chalupin*. I'm
going to give you my car. Who has to give the handkerchief
to whom? So that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. It
could be I'm going to give it to you, Jonathan, the seller
or the buyer. So one says point is, is says that the
buyer does. You give me your handkerchief and I give you my
car. That's at least more modeled after an idea of barter, again,
even though it's very different in terms of what really is being
exchanged. But there's one opinion that says I give you the handkerchief
and I give and therefore you get the car. Now that's clearly
not modeled after barter. But if it's a signal of גמר דעת
g'mar da'at, *Gmar Daas*, it makes a lot of sense.
It's a symbolic מחשבה *Machshava*.
Right? It could be a symbolic מחשבה *Machshava*. I am showing, I
am symbolizing my transferring of my car by giving you my handkerchief,
and you take my handkerchief. I am signifying my obligating myself to
the terms of the contract by my giving you my handkerchief. That
conceptually could easily be קונה koneh *Koneh* or מקנה *Makneh* if it's
just to signify גמר דעת *Gmar Daas*. So it's clearly a very
different model and phenomenon than barter. Now the problem is, is that
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to like equate the two and
sort of assume that it's all the same rules govern both of
them, okay? Which leads to תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
doesn't play this out, but I just want to point out how
absurd this becomes. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says if that's true, in the
case of the cow and the donkey, if we would apply the
exact same rules of the handkerchief to the cow and the donkey,
so if you פסקן *Pasken* by the handkerchief it's בכלי של מקנה
*B'keli Shel Makneh*, so do you know what we're talking about in
the cow and the donkey? It's not I take your cow and
you get my donkey. It's I give you my cow and you
also get my donkey. That's what the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* would be
talking about, which is like crazy! Like, what's that? חליפין chalipin *Chalupin*
is I give you one object and you get the other object.
Like, that's not חליפין chalipin, *Chalupin*, that's maybe like אגב *Agav*, I
don't know what that is. But that's not חליפין chalipin, *Chalupin*. Okay,
but תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, and we're not going to go through it,
but תוספות *Tosfos* plays out the whole issue of the cow and
the donkey and the barter, assuming that you could just as well
go by the כלי kli. *Keli*, it could be the seller just
as much as the buyer. But logically, of course, these are very
different. There's the model of barter, which is clearly I give you
one object and I get your object in exchange. Then there's this
object about like a signifier of גמר דעת *Gmar Daas*, קנין סודר
kinyan sudar *Kinyan Sudar*, which then we could talk about, you don't
have to let go of it, you could get it back, it
could be this person's כלי kli, *Keli*, that person's כלי kli *Keli*,
it could go either way. Okay, so we have those two models
in mind, and let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* as we try to figure out what is כל הנעשה דמים
באחר kol hana'aseh damim be'acher, *Kol HaNasah Damim B'acher*, what that means.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חליפין chalipin מאי ניהו *Chalupin
mai nihu*? So what type of חליפין chalipin? *Chalupin* are we talking
about in the beginning of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*? Even the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* is not so clear, is hard to parse. Okay, so
I'm going to read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* tells
us pretty much to read it the same way, but even the
words of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* are not so transparent. Okay, when
we say that נעשה דמים באחר na'aseh damim be'acher *Nasah damim b'acher*,
we're talking about a חליפין chalipin. *Chalupin*, what are we referring to?
מטבע matbea, *Matbeia*, a coin. So what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says this
means is כל הנעשה דמים באחר kol ha-na'aseh damim b'acher, *Kol HaNasah
Damim B'acher* means the following. Okay, if I wanted to pay you
$20, whatever, $200 for your donkey and I gave you $200, would
that work? Let me say it again. I wanted to pay, buy
your donkey for $200. I gave you $200 cash. Is that a
קנין kinyan *Kinyan*? קנין כסף kinyan kessef *Kinyan Kesef*, does it work
by מטלטלין metaltelin. *Metaltelin*? No. Good, somebody's been paying attention. Okay, so
cash doesn't work. I would have to do משיכה Meshicha. *Meshicha*, right?
So this $200 is נעשה דמים na'aseh damim באחר *Nasah damim b'acher*.
Under most circumstances, what do I use this $200 as? I use
it as money. I use it to pay for what the object
costs. But let's say what we're going to say is, I'm not
going to treat this as money, I'm going to treat this as
an object. I will swap you my pile of coins here for
your donkey. I'm not paying for your donkey. We're swapping. Okay, it's
just a slightly, it's like a conceptual shift. Imagine we lived in
a world in which things weren't monetized and there wasn't a dollar
tag on every type of a thing, and money wasn't a way
of determining something's value, and we just had objects. If we just
had objects, here, I have some objects, I have some nice little
green paper here with different numbers on it, okay, I have a
nice little pile of coins, and we'll swap my little pile of
coins for your little thing. So this thing under normal circumstances would
be considered money and דמים *Damim*, and it would be the way
of paying. paying for the cost and then it would be akin
to כסף kessef and that wouldn't work. But if you want to
call it חליפין, chalipin. we'll swap this money for your for your
cow, that can work. So it won't work as כסף kessef but
it will look as חליפין. chalipin. And the חידוש chiddush is that
the that חליפין chalipin, can work even with a מטבע, matbea even
with a coin if the coin is being treated as an object
and not as money. Yes.
Okay, first of all, with the green pieces of paper, I only
want the pictures of Benjamin Franklin. Gotcha. Okay. Second of all,
why is it though, like I get it, right, money is abstract,
it's not an object. You're not really קונה anything. So then you
give me your $200, I don't give you my cow. Right. So
why am I a scoundrel? But
why am I a scoundrel?
What do you mean, if I paid קנין כסף kinyan kesef. and
you didn't give it to me? Yeah. What do you mean because
of מי שפרע? mi she-para? Why you're a scoundrel?
המשיך ועשה...
hemshich ve'assa... right, you haven't קונה my cow, but you gave me
the 200.
So you'd have to give me it back if you didn't follow
through.
Why is that?
Why, why? I don't understand what you're asking. I paid you money
for your thing, the sale wasn't final, so if the sale never
goes through, you have to give me back the money that I
paid you for the
thing.
Okay, so the price is the price for the market.
Right. Yeah. So you don't see how you can consider מטבע matbea
an object. מטבע matbea is always payment.
No, but just in that
case if you give him five $50 bills
and he could theoretically give you back five singles.
No, it's whatever you agreed to. If I'm going to, like, you're
not giving him money, you're just giving him five dollar bills.
Yeah, but we agreed to a particular type of a pile of
bills. We agreed to particular types of coins. Okay. Let's assume, let's
assume that we were talking about my coin collection, okay? And it,
right, so we can exchange my coin collection, that's a great example
actually. We can exchange my coin collection for your cow, right?
So this just happens to be a coin collection of all new
$50 bills. That's my coin collection. That's a coin collection. But if
you give me something else, that's not the coin collection I agreed
on.
Okay, making a very fine distinction between כסף kesef and...
right, we're treating it not as abstract and value and whatever, we're
treating it as this physical object. Right. I mean, I guess, look,
this would be an interesting question. Let's say I would say I'll
swap you, and I use the language of חליפין, chalipin. I'll swap
you, you know, this coin for your cow. And then when it
came time to do it, accidentally I gave you a I gave
you a different coin of the same color and things. So could
you say, well, that wasn't the agreement? I don't know, maybe you
could. Okay. So it's obviously it's a little bit of a fiction
here and in the end we פוסק posek that מטבע matbea. is
לא נעשה חליפין. lo na'aseh chalipin. But that's the way the גמרא
Gemara wants to read it, okay? נעשה na'aseh דמים באחר means under
normal circumstances this would be money. But if you want to treat
it as an object and do חליפין, chalipin. you can do חליפין
chalipin. with it. Okay, מטבע. matbea שמע מינה מטבע נעשה חליפין. shema
mina matbea na'aseh chalipin. So are we, are we supposed to infer
that a מטבע matbea can be חליפין? chalipin. Normally we assume that
a מטבע matbei'a, cannot be חליפין. chalipin, So אמר רב יהודה הכי
קאמר, Amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, this is what we're saying. כל
הנישום דמים באחר, kol hanishom damim be'acher,
כיון שזכה זה keivan shezachah zeh, נתחייב בחליפיו. nitchayav bechalifav. Anything that
is normally assessed for value, okay, can be made an object of
חליפין. chalipin? Meaning what? That means the exact opposite. Meaning anything that
is not money. That any object that has to be assessed what
its value is, meaning that it is not itself money, can be
an object of חליפין. chalipin But cash, which is not an object
of חליפין, chalipin, because cash isn't an object, cash is the value.
So anything that is given a value outside of itself, okay, is
assigned a value and assessed a value, meaning anything that is not
cash can be an object of חליפין. chalipin. As opposed to cash
itself, which cannot be. Is that clear how we're reading it now?
כל הנישום דמים באחר kol hanishom damim be'acher means, right, כל הנעשה
דמים באחר, kol ha-na'aseh damim b'acher anything that has to be converted,
maybe the better word here would be converted. Anything that has to
be converted into cash is appraised, but even the word נעשה is
like anything that needs to be converted to cash is an object
that you could do חליפין. chalipin. So what's the only thing that
doesn't need to be converted into cash? Cash! So anything other than
cash can be an object of חליפין.
chalipin, What does נישום nishom here mean?
Assess. It has to be assessed for its value. שומא. shuma.
Oh, it's a נפעל nifal of שומא. shuma. Amazing.
Yeah. Okay, so you bet you can be amazed by grammar. כל
הכבוד לך. kol hakavod lach. Okay. Now, דיקא נמי, deika nami, that
also is a good read can be of the משנה. Mishnah
דתני, detani, because the remainder of the משנה Mishnah? says, כיצד החליף
שור בפרה או חמור בשור. keitzad hechlif shor befarah o chamor beshor.
So we're talking not about cash, we're talking about normal objects. שמע
מינה. shema mina. So you see that the beginning of the משנה
Mishnah. was not talking about cash, because then כיצד keitzad would not
be a good illustration. כיצד keitzad means it's illustrating. So if the
ox and the donkey are illustrating, clearly what we're talking about is
דוקא davka not cash. Only things that are not cash can be
חליפין. chalipin, Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ולמאי
דסליק אדעתין ul'mai desalik adaitin It's going to be a very interesting
גמרא, Gemara. it's going to try to figure out a הוה אמינא
hava amina that we just rejected. Okay, but based on our הוה
אמינא hava amina מעיקרא mei'ikara דמתניתין נעשה חליפין dematnitin na'aseh chalipin that
we read that first phrase of נעשה דמים to mean you can
use money as חליפין, chalipin. so מאי כיצד? mai keitzad? How do
you read the כיצד keitzad of the משנה? Mishnah. What was that
הוה אמינא? hava amina? How would the כיצד keitzad of the cow
and the donkey be illustrating the idea that a coin could be
חליפין? chalipin, So right, got the question?
So it says everybody listen here? Yes? Okay, הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar.
So here's what it's saying. פירות נמי עבדי חליפין. peirot nami avdei
chalipin. By the way, not only money, but even פירות, peirot, even
you know, פירות peirot is a generic term for like other objects.
Okay,
כיצד? keitzad? החליף בשר שור בפרה hechlip basar shor b'parah או בשר
חמור בשור, o basar chamor b'shor, for example if you swapped, and
now we're going to, it's interesting, it adds the word בשר basar
because it wants to make it something that's much more like consumables,
like food, okay, so if you swapped you know, the meat of
an ox for a donkey or בשר חמור, basar chamor, I don't
know what you're using בשר חמור basar chamor for, for your dog
food I guess, okay, בשור, b'shor, כיון שזכה זה נתחייב בחליפין. keivan
she-zachah zeh nitchayev b'chalipin. Okay, so therefore, here's the way to read
the משנה. Mishnah. Now the other thing you have to know about
חליפין chalipin. is, there are basically three categories.
There's מטבע, matbei'a,
פירות, peirot, and כלי. kli, The thing that obviously is the חליפין,
chalipin, now this is normally in the context that we discussed it,
but the גמרא Gemara, here is conflating the two, but we normally
discuss it in the context of קנין kinyan סודר. So the basis
for the קנין kinyan? סודר is the פסוק pasuk in רות Rut
which says, right, ושלף איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו, v'shalaf ish na'alo u-natan
l'rei'eihu, right? People know that, right? נעלו ונתן לרעהו, na'alo u-natan l'rei'eihu,
right? And that's that, you know, and that's how you do וזאת
לתעודה בישראל, v'zot l'te'udah b'Yisrael, right? That's the פסוק pasuk that says
you give somebody your shoe, whatever, that creates a גמר דעת, that
signifies the context. So that's a כלי, kli. okay, that's נעלו. na'alo.
So we know that a כלי kli works for חליפין. chalipin, Alright,
מטבע, like that's money, that's the stuff that's hardest to understand as
חליפין. chalipin. That's normally a קנין כסף. kinyan kesef, Alright, the פירות
peirot is a middle category. פירות peirot is stuff like you know
food, okay, which is not a כלי, kli which is not an
instrument, okay, but it's like consumables, it's other, all other objects of
value that are neither instruments nor are they, you know, vessels, like
you know functional types of instruments, and nor are they cash. Alright.
So the גמרא Gemara here, there's a whole question how to read
the גמרא here, but רש"י Rashi and תוספות assume where would you
put בשר שור? basar shor? Let's start with that. Where would you
put meat? Under which of these three categories? פירות. peirot. פירות, peirot,
okay. Where would you put a שור? shor? כלי. kli So that's
the question. Is a שור shor like a כלי kli? because it's
something you use? Right, or it's not a כלי kli because it's
not manufactured? Where, what exactly defines כלי kli, or not כלי? kli,
Okay. So where does
the שור shor
go? Function or origin?
Right. So רש"י and תוספות basically assume for the, to
read this גמרא, that
even שור shor would
be here, which makes it funny why the גמרא had to switch
to בשר שור. basar shor. Okay.
So basically what we're saying is like this. So you have these
three categories. Okay. So here's our משנה. Mishnah כל הנעשה דמים באחר,
and then it's the כיצד, keitzad, and it's the
שור וחמור, shor v'chamor, okay? So this case of שור וחמור, shor
v'chamor, okay, that that works for חליפין, chalipin, and then we're assuming
again, by the way, barter and the קנין kinyan סודר have the
same rules. Okay. So this idea that the שור shor and the
חמור chamor work for חליפין, chalipin, okay, we are saying is a
case of basically, well, either כלי kli or if you say שור
וחמור shor v'chamor is כלי, or פירות. peirot. פירות peirot work for
חליפין. chalipin. That's the כיצד. keitzad. What does כל הנעשה דמים באחר
mean? So there was two interpretations. Number one was cash, which means
cash is חליפין, chalipin. we rejected that. And number two means anything
that's not cash. Okay. Right? Those were our two explanations. Yes. Of
what what that means. So in explanation number two is anything that's
not cash works in חליפין. Chalipin. So as long as you're not
cash, for example this, so you've got basically, you know, פירות, peirot,
something that's not cash, it all works very nice. But the גמרא
says, but if you say cash works for חליפין, Chalipin what's the
כיצד? keitzad? So it said well, the כיצד keitzad isn't saying that
this is, it's saying and not only cash works for חליפין, Chalipin,
פירות peirot also work for חליפין. Chalipin Okay. So there's two ways
to read the משנה. Mishna, Either not cash works for חליפין, for
example פירות, peirot, okay, but only פירות peirot and not cash. That's
the way we ended. And the first way to read the משנה
Mishna, which we rejected is, cash works for חליפין, and not only
cash, that's כיצד, keitzad, but in addition, cash works and also פירות
peirot work. Okay. But according to both of those reads, we're saying
that פירות peirot works for חליפין.
So if you say cash works, then you've also
got, yeah, yeah,
okay, but let's now continue because now regarding, regardless of the read,
we're saying that פירות peirot work for חליפין. So now the גמרא
says like this:
הניחא
לרב ששת דאמר פירות עבדי חליפין, Hani'cha le'Rav Sheshet de'amar Peros avdei
Chalipin, fine. Yes. Yes.
It just seems פירות Peros is a different category though, especially if
we're talking about a scenario where one takes their object, the other
one already has responsibility for the other object. פירות Peros spoil.
Well, that's true, but you
know,
I mean, I get it, but that's like your responsibility to take
care of it. Right. But I do get that. All right. So
the גמרא says: הניחא לרב ששת דאמר פירות עבדי חליפין. Hani'cha le'Rav
Sheshet de'amar Peros avdei Chalipin. So look, that's a good read of
the משנה, Mishna? either of these two reads. The way רש"י and
תוספות say that the question we're asking now is both reads. Because
both reads are assuming that שור וחמור Shor ve'Chamur is not just
בשר שור, besar shor, but even a real שור shor is in
the פירות Peros category.
So either of these reads of the משנה, Mishna. the שור וחמור
Shor ve'Chamur works, but it only works if you assume that you
can use פירות Peros for
חליפין. הניחא לרב ששת דאמר פירות עבדי חליפין. Hani'cha le'Rav Sheshet de'amar
Peros avdei Chalipin. אלא לרב נחמן דאמר פירות לא עבדי חליפין, Ella
le'Rav Nachman de'amar Peros lo avdei Chalipin, you can only do חליפין
with a כלי, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le'meimar? How do you
read the משנה? Mishna. So, yeah, it's a real big problem because
there's no כלי in the משנה. Mishna. הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. Here's
how to read the משנה. Mishna, ויש דמים שהן כחליפין. Veyesh damim
shehen ke'Chalipin. Now this is going to be a complete reread of
the משנה. Mishna, There are some times money works as like חליפין,
but really we're not talking about חליפין at all. What's the example?
So, כיצד? Keitzad? החליף דמי שור בפרה או דמי חמור בשור. Hechlif
dmei shor be'parah o dmei chamor be'shor. Okay? So, for example, if
you exchange the money of an ox with a cow, or the
money of a mule with an ox. What does that mean?
So basically what it means is the following. It means I go
to Dove there and I say, Dove, you want to buy my
cow? And Dove says, sure. How much? $100. Fine. Here's the cow.
Do משיכה. Meshicha, So you now owe me $100 for my cow.
That's דמי פרה. dmei parah. You owe me that $100. Okay? Then
I say to Dove, I say, you know what Dove? I hear
that actually you've got a mule to sell. Is that right? Tell
you what Dove, let me take that mule for the $100 that
you already owe me for my cow. And you say sure. Okay.
Sure.
You missed the part, you said sure. Exactly. Okay, exactly. Anyway, so
you say no problem. So now what happens is I now own
your donkey with the דמי פרה. dmei parah. The money you owed
me for the cow that you have not yet paid, that money
now you get to keep and that lets me own your donkey.
So what type of a קנין kinyan, or mule, what type of
a קנין is that? It sounds like a קנין כסף, kinyan kesef
but קנין כסף kinyan kesef doesn't work by מטלטלין. metaltelin. So here
we're going to explain how it works. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? סבר
לה כרבי יוחנן. Savar lah ke'Rabbi Yochanan. He holds like רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר, De'amar, דבר תורה, dvar Torah, biblically speaking, מעות קונות,
Maos konos, כסף kesef actually works for מטלטלין. metaltelin, ומה טעם אמרו
משיכה קונה? U'mah ta'am amru Meshicha konah?
So why did we say כסף kesef doesn't work and you have
to do משיכה, Meshicha. you have to take the object into your
possession? שמא יאמר לו נשרפו חיטיך בעלייה, Shema yomar lo nisrefu chitecha
ba'aliyah,
because you'll give me the money and I won't deliver the product
to you and it'll already be your product and then I'll say,
oh, an accident happened and the product got destroyed or whatever. Meaning
I won't be even liable, but I have no incentive to protect
the object now. It's your object, you're the one responsible, I'm not
the one responsible.
And therefore, so therefore we said that we're going to annul the
קנין of כסף kesef, and we're going to replace it with a
קנין of משיכה. Meshicha. But now we're saying the following: מילתא דשכיחא
גזרו בה רבנן. Milta de'shchicha gazru bah rabanan.
A common scenario, that's where
we implemented this rule. And we said no longer כסף, kessef, just
משיכה. Meshicha, מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן. Milta d'lo shchicha
lo gazru bah rabanan.
But something that's less common, we go back, we did not implement
our rule and we let the normal biblical קנין כסף kinyan kesef,
take place. Okay? So this is like completely crazy. Basically what it
is saying is that we have, first step is we did away
with קנין כסף, kinyan kesef we replaced it with קנין משיכה. kinyan
Meshicha. But now we're going to say, you know, in scenarios that
are not so common, then we'll let the old קנין כסף kinyan
kesef, work as it used to work. Just like, and who gets
to determine what parameters determine commonality? Like I don't know, if I'm
buying your Ferrari, you know, it's pretty uncommon for people to sell
Ferraris. So I mean what makes it uncommon, right? Why is this
דווקא davka the scenario that we identify? And what type of a
sense does it make? What's the incentive to have loopholes, to have
these like holes in the system, right? Not to have like one
basic rule of how קנינים kinyanim work? This really makes like no
sense. But in order to explain the משנה, Mishna what we're saying
is if I'm not giving you cash, what I'm doing is I'm
letting you keep the money you owe me for an earlier transaction,
then I don't have to do משיכה, meshika. then you can just,
I can just own it by letting you keep that money. If
anything, that's like such a weak. קניין *kinyan*, it’s all abstract. Nothing
is changing hands. Something happened in the past, nothing is happening now.
If there’s any place that a קניין *kinyan*, that that כסף kessef.
*kesef* should not work, it would be that case, right? And there
we’re saying that כסף kessef *kesef* works. All right, so it’s a
very pressed read of the משנה Mishna *mishna*. Difficult read. So the
משנה Mishna. *mishna*, let me just explain again. The משנה *mishna* simply
is talking about חליפין *chalipin*. It’s
clearly this case about the ox and the donkey is talking about
a case of פירות *peiros*, assuming that they go in the פירות
*peira* category not the כלי *kli* category. So that only works according
to the opinion that פירות *peiros* works for חליפין *chalipin*. But if
the only thing that works for חליפין *chalipin* is a כלי *kli*,
there’s no way to explain this משנה *mishna* to be about חליפין
*chalipin*. So rather than explain this משנה *mishna* that seems all about
teaching about חליפין *chalipin*, we’re saying no, the משנה *mishna* is saying
something that normally you owe me the money for or something that
normally would be like, you know, a purchase with money, if it’s
basically letting you keep money that you owe me from an earlier
purchase, then it works to be קונה *koneh*. That’s what the משנה
*mishna* is saying. Crazy read of the משנה *mishna*.
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* holds that דבר תורה Torah, *devar Torah* קניין
דמים *kinyan damim* is קונה *koneh*.
So that’s the סוגיא *sugya* in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia. *Bava Metzia*.
I mean, very nice but yeah. So it’s but I don’t want
to get into that now. But what I want to point out
is by the way is that the whole reason we’re forced into
this, well, it was two reasons. Number one is because we’re categorizing
שור וחמור *shor v’chamor* in פירות *peiros* rather than כלי *kli*, and
רש"י *Rashi* already points out that logically you could put them in
כלי *kli*. But the bigger thing that gets me upset is that
this issue is about the קניין סודר *kinyan sudar*. Right, it’s basically
this פסוק *pasuk*: שלף איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו וזאת התעודה בישראל *sholaf
ish na’alo venatan lere’ehu vezot hate’udah beyisrael*. This is how you like,
that’s the קניין *kinyan* of the גמרא *Gemara* דף *daf*. That’s the
קניין *kinyan* of the סודר *sudar*. Right, you could understand that, okay,
a handkerchief or whatever, something like that, that formalizes it. But if
you’re talking about barter and swapping, there’s no reason to exclude פירות
*peiros*. Why can’t we swap? I mean, well you said maybe they
rot. But still, like fundamentally
you should not be making different categories. The fact is, the funny
thing is that the גמרא *Gemara*’s taking this which is about swapping
and applying these categories which are really about a discussion of קניין
סודר *kinyan sudar*. All right, and the גמרא *Gemara* seeing them all
the same. Let’s just finish up this גמרא *Gemara*.
ולריש לקיש *U’leReish Lakish* דאמר *dishamar* משיכה meshika, מפורשת מן התורה *meshicha
meforeshet min haTorah*. Now ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, you don’t have this
crazy read of the משנה *mishna* according to
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, because ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says משיכה meshika
*meshicha*’s explicit in the תורה *Torah* for מטלטלין metaltelin, *metaltelin*. So according
to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, הניחא *hani’cha* אי סבר
לה *i savar lah* כרב ששת *k’Rav
Sheshet*, right? So this משנה *mishna* now cannot be talking about a
weird קניין כסף kessef *kinyan kesef* because he doesn’t have a קניין
כסף kesef, *kinyan kesef*. So clearly the שור *shor* and the חמור
*chamor* is talking about a קניין חליפין *kinyan chalipin* that works with
פירות *peiros*. So הניחא *hani’cha* that works אי סבר לה *i savar
lah* כרב ששת *k’Rav Sheshet* דאמר פירות עבדי חליפין *d’amar peiros avdi
chalipin*. מתרץ כרב ששת *Metaretz k’Rav Sheshet*. So then he says, so
פירות *peiros* does it, so that’s what we’re talking about. Swapping a
שור וחמור *shor v’chamor* is a חליפין *chalipin* of פירות *peiros*. Okay,
that would work. אלא אי סבר לה *Ella i savar lah* כרב
נחמן *k’Rav Nachman* דאמר פירות לא עבדי חליפין *d’amar peiros lo avdi
chalipin*. But if he holds like רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* that פירות
*peiros* don’t do חליפין *chalipin*, so this doesn’t work. Okay, ומטבע לא
קני *u’matbea lo kani*, and we already said that money isn’t. So
if money isn’t and פירות *peiros* isn’t, so what’s the משנה *mishna*
talking about? It’s not talking about money for חליפין *chalipin*, it’s not
talking about פירות *peiros* for חליפין *chalipin*, it’s not talking about a
weird קניין כסף kesef *kinyan kesef* because ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* doesn’t
hold of a קניין כסף kesef *kinyan kesef*. There’s nothing the משנה
*mishna* could be talking about. So במאי מוקמי לה *bemai mokivei lah*?
What’s the משנה *mishna* talking about? על כרחך *Al korchecha* כרב ששת
*k’Rav Sheshet* סבירא ליה *sevira leh*. Oh, it must be like we
said that he holds like רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* that פירות *peiros*
do חליפין *chalipin* and that’s the שור *shor* and the חמור *chamor*.
Okay.
So, bottom line is, the simple read of the משנה *mishna*, put
the גמרא *Gemara* aside, is you don’t want to introduce any of
the discussion of פירות עבדי חליפין *peiros avdi chalipin* or any of
that stuff, because we’re talking here about barter, we’re not talking about
קניין סודר *kinyan sudar*. But the גמרא *Gemara* assumes, no, no, no,
we have to bring in the discussion
about קניין סודר *kinyan sudar* about פירות *peiros*, etc. So what does
the משנה *mishna* mean? So number one, כל הנעשה דמים באחר *kol
hana’aseh damim b’acher* has two possible meanings. Either it means you can
use money for חליפין *chalipin*, which is very strange, and the גמרא
*Gemara* rejects that. Or it means the exact opposite: something that can
be converted into money, meaning you can use not-money for חליפין *chalipin*.
Something that isn’t cash can be used for חליפין *chalipin* and the
example is an ox and a donkey. And what that shows you
is that חליפין *chalipin* can be not only with a כלי *kli*
but even with פירות *peiros*. Okay, and that’s the read of the
משנה *mishna*. כלי *kli* yes, פירות *peiros* yes, cash no.
Okay, Rabbi Yisrael, could you just remind us what’s רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman*’s סברא *sevarah*? Why did he conclude that פירות *peiros* do
not?
The סברא *sevarah* is based just on the פסוק *pasuk*. It says
נעלו *na’alo*.
So do you read נעלו *na’alo* as דווקא *davka* נעלו *na’alo* and
therefore a כלי *kli*? Or I think there’s a ריבוי *ribuy* of
like לקיים כל דבר *lekayem kol davar* or something like that.
That’s on the סוגיא *sugya* הזהב *HaZahav*.
Yeah, it’s just based on
that פסוק *pasuk*. But
again, all of this... to the type of a barter type of
a חליפין. All right, let's move on.
Now we go to another משנה, there also, as you'll see, is
a little bit of an archaic language, but not as cryptic. Okay,
and here's what it says: רשות הגבוה בכסף ורשות ההדיוט בחזקה. Reshus
hagavoah bekesef ureshus hahedyot bachazaka.
So what we would call in more contemporary, like in the more
contemporary Mishnaic language of הקדש, hekdesh, okay, you know things that are
הקדש hekdesh that belong to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, this earlier
משנה refers to as רשות גבוה. reshus gavoah. The property of the
Most High, okay, so it means הקדש, hekdesh, okay, and as opposed
to רשות הדיוט, reshus hedyot, the property of, we call it הקדש
וחולין, hekdesh vechulin, right, people hear that? We call it הקדש וחולין
hekdesh vechulin and the משנה calls it רשות גבוה ורשות הדיוט. reshus
gavoah ureshus hedyot. It's an earlier משנה. רשות הגבוה בכסף, Reshus hagavoah
bekesef, so הקדש hekdesh takes possession of things with a קנין כסף,
kinyan kesef even מטלטלין, metaltelin but רשות ההדיוט בחזקה, reshus hahedyot bachazaka,
but a normal person, a lay person, takes possession of things with
חזקה, chazaka, which basically means taking physical possession. It could be if
it's קרקע, karka, it would mean חזקה, chazaka, if it's מטלטלין, it
would mean משיכה. meshicha Okay, הקדש hekdesh does it with money, but
a הדיוט hedyot does it as we've been seeing with physical possession.
אמירתו לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט, Amiraso legavoah kimesiraso lehedyot, and not only that,
but just your verbal saying something belongs to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash is like you physically would have handed it over to another
person. So what would be an example of that? I say, this
ox is a קרבן. korban. I say, I'm מקדיש makdish my cow.
Does הקדש hekdesh have to do a קנין? No, the words themselves
have the effect of transferring the ownership to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Okay, so my אמירה, amira, all along we've been talking about
physical possession, מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, etc. By הקדש hekdesh your words
just do it. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: כיצד רשות הגבוה בכסף? Keitzad reshus hagavoah bekesef?
What what does this mean that הקדש hekdesh takes possession of something
with money? Okay, גזבר, gizbar, because we just said your words, okay,
but there are also cases where it's not your words. So גזבר
שנתן מעות בבהמה. gizbar shenasan maos bebehema. I here, I'm the treasurer
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and I'm going to go out
and I need to buy some animals, I need to buy I
don't know some, some sheep for a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur or
something. Okay, אפילו בהמה בסוף העולם קנה. afilu behema besof haolam kana.
So Dov tells me he's got some sheep grazing in New Zealand,
they're very good sheep, I hear it's good grazing areas there. So
I'm going to give him the money now, and I own those
sheep in New Zealand even if they're בסוף העולם, besof haolam, okay,
even though by הדיוט hedyot of course that wouldn't work, there's not
a קנין כסף Kinyan kesef. by מטלטלין by הדיוט. hedyot. ובהדיוט לא
קנה עד שימשוך. Uvehedyot lo kana ad sheyimshoch. Okay, but by הדיוט
hedyot I would not take possession of those sheep until I did
משיכה, meshicha but here the, the money is enough. Now what you
might be thinking is, is this good thing for הקדש hekdesh or
not a good thing? Because we just said before that if I
own them as soon as I pay the money, that means that
if something happens to them between getting them from New Zealand to
here, it's my loss, not, not Dov's loss, right?
Yes, it's a type of a קנין though, right? קנין כסף.
kinyan kessef. Right, right. But that works for הקדש, hekdesh, it doesn't
work for הדיוט. hedyot. But the question you should be asking is,
is that in הקדש's hekdesh best interest? Because the whole reason that
we said by הדיוט hedyot you have to take possession is to
protect the buyer. So why is that in הקדש's hekdesh best interest?
So we'll have to we'll come back to that.
Okay, כיצד אמירתו לגבוה כמסירתו להדיוט? Keitzad amiraso legavoah kimesiraso lehedyot? Now,
what does this mean that saying something is belongs to God is
like giving something over to a person?
האומר שור זה עולה בית זה הקדש, Ha'omer shor zeh olah bayis
zeh hekdesh, whether it's about a קרבן korban or whether it's about
transferring ownership, this ox is an עולה olah or this house is
הקדש, hekdesh, אפילו בסוף העולם קנה, afilu besof haolam kana, even if
they're at the other ends of the world, that works just by
your verbal statement. ובהדיוט עד שלא קנה עד שימשוך ויחזיק. Uvehedyot ad
lo kana ad sheyimshoch veyachazik. But by a normal person you would
have to do משיכה meshicha by the cow and חזקה chazaka by
the house. You would have to do an actual act, here the
words work. Now I want to stop for a minute and say
something about the idea that the words work. Why they work by
a קרבן korban is more obvious. Because by a קרבן, korban, right,
I mean for people remembered when we did נדרים Nedarim and what
not, right, you have this whole idea of הפלאה, hafla'ah, my words
can create changes of status. My words can take this animal and
give it קדושה, kedusha, make it a קרבן. korban. Okay, but that
fundamentally doesn't start in the world of ownership. There are some קרבנות
korbanos that even I am considered to own, like a קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, since I'm going to
eat the meat of a שלמים, shelamim, to some degree. Give me
a. Oh, shush. No, that's my Siri. Okay, קדשים קלים kodashim kalim
I'm going to according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, I'm considered actually
to be the owner of קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. The idea of
a קדושה kedusha of a קרבן korban is not fundamentally, if I
said to you, what does this mean that this animal is an
עולה? olah? Would the first thing you say is, oh, it means
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash owns it? No, it's not a question
of ownership. Who's talking about ownership? It has something to do with
the intrinsic status of the animal, right? Its state, its of הקדש.
hekdesh. So there...
So that's so what I'm saying relates to, מעילה meilah might be
misuse, not theft. That's a good question. That's the whole question of
מעילה. meilah. That's a good question. Okay, so by the הקדש hekdesh
we deal with two ideas. One is the status of the object.
It's הקדש, hekdesh, it's a קדושה kedusha cannot be violated, cannot be
misused and so on. The other is the ownership question. Okay, now
when I'm מקדיש makdish my house, the basic purpose of being מקדיש
makdish my house is to do what? It's because I want to
make a donation to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So there it
is much more about transfer of ownership than it is about, you
know, instilling a status. So there's a bigger חידוש, chiddush, there's not
such a חידוש chiddush that I can make something a קרבן korban
with my words. There is a bigger חידוש chiddush that I can
transfer ownership, but that's in the תורה, איש כי יקדיש את ביתו
קודש להשם, ish ki yakdish es beiso kodesh l'Hashem, right?
If you sanctify it. So just designating it as holy is enough
even though the purpose is fundamentally not about the status but more
about transfer. Nevertheless, that's the power of הקדש, hekdesh, that your words
which make it הקדש hekdesh are words that also transfer ownership. Okay,
so that's אמירה לגבוה כמסירה להדיוט. amira l'gavoha k'mesira l'hedyot. Now, we're
going to read a little bit about how this idea of the
money, does that help הקדש hekdesh or not help הקדש? hekdesh? So
let's take a look. משכו במנה. mashchu b'maneh.
Now, I agreed to buy your sheep in New Zealand there,
or whatever, your sheep for a hundred dollars. I'm the גזבר. gizbar.
ולא הספיק לפדותו עד שעמד במאתים. v'lo hispik lifdoso ad she'amad b'masayim.
So, I'm sorry, no no no, we're not talking about this purchaser.
So somebody bought something from הקדש, hekdesh, okay, and he paid a
hundred dollars and he bought it from הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, and he
did a משיכה meshicha but he did not pay the money yet,
that's the phase of לפדותו lifdoso because the paying of the money
removes the קדושה kedusha status from the object. So I'm buying this,
I don't know, car off of הקדש, hekdesh, okay? So instead of
Cars for Kids we have cars for הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so I'm
selling, I'm sorry, I'm buying this car off of הקדש hekdesh for
a hundred dollars and I haven't yet paid the
money, עד שעמד במאתים, ad she'amad b'masayim, and then the market changed
and now it's worth two hundred. So now that we know that
הקדש hekdesh goes by כסף, kesef what would you say? Who owns
this car at this moment? I did משיכה meshicha? but I haven't
paid for it. Who owns it? I did משיכה meshicha. from הקדש.
hekdesh. I took this car from הקדש. hekdesh. Who owns it now?
I did משיכה meshicha without paying.
Come on.
What?
You said הקדש hekdesh goes by money. So if הקדש hekdesh goes
by money, who owns it now?
I took it from him.
I took it, but let's assume it's parallel, okay, like we didn't
say that, but assume it's parallel. So I took this from הקדש,
hekdesh, I haven't paid the money, so it still belongs to הקדש.
hekdesh. I haven't paid the money. So now it goes up to
two hundred.
What's the effect of the משיכה?
meshicha Nothing, absolutely nothing. So it's now gone up to two hundred,
הקדש hekdesh is now entitled to charge me two hundred. I don't
own it yet. Okay? עד שעמד במאתים נותן מאתים, ad she'amad b'masayim
nosein masayim, I have to give two hundred. I didn't own it
yet.
Why? Because the verbal agreement was for a hundred.
Who cares? The sale wasn't final, that's why you have a קנין,
because it's not final till it's final. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? ונתן
הכסף וקם לו. v'nasan hakessef v'kam lo. That's where we have the
idea that הקדש hekdesh works by כסף. You give the money and
then you get it. Okay, so by הקדש hekdesh it's with money.
So if I haven't given the money yet, they can charge me
whatever they want now and if the price went up, they can
raise it. Now, what about if it's the reverse? משכו במאתים, mashchu
b'masayim, it was worth two hundred and I did a משיכה. meshicha,
ולא הספיק לפדותו עד שעמד במנה, v'lo hispik lifdoso ad she'amad b'maneh,
now it's gone down to a hundred. Now you should think I
should be entitled to say to הקדש, hekdesh, one minute, it's not
final, I didn't pay the money, I'm going to give you only
a hundred for it. No. נותן מאתים, nosein masayim, I have to
give two hundred. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? לא יהיה כח הדיוט חמור
מהקדש, lo yehei koach hedyot chamur mehekdesh, because a layperson should not
have greater rights and power than הקדש. hekdesh. So basically it means
the issue I raised earlier is if הקדש's hekdesh interest to be
with money, sometimes that works against your interests. So the answer is
like, you know, what's the, what's it like? The house, what is
it, the odds are always in favor of the house?
The deck is stacked.
The deck is stacked in favor of the house. So the קניינים
kinyanim are stacked in favor of the house, I mean the הקדש.
hekdesh. Right, the קניינים kinyanim are stacked in favor of הקדש. hekdesh.
הקדש hekdesh owns it with כסף or with משיכה meshicha based on
what serves הקדש's hekdesh best interest.
Okay, so let's even, for example, we're not talking about הקדש, hekdesh,
right? You give me money for my sheep which is in New
Zealand. Right. Okay, and the sheep dies. Right. That's your problem, right?
No, I didn't do משיכה meshicha, yet. The sale was never final,
give me my money back.
Okay, so it's not, right, so there was no, okay, fine.
Right. Let's just read the end here. פדהו במאתים, padahu b'masayim, let's
say the opposite, okay, let's say you didn't start with משיכה, meshicha,
you started with money.
What if instead of giving him money, you gave him a cow
for a sheep?
Yes, correct.
And the sheep died?
Then I would have lost the
money, yep. פדהו במאתים, padahu b'masayim, now you started with cash. I
gave the two hundred to הקדש hekdesh for the car.
ולא הספיק למשכו עד שעמד במנה, v'lo hispik limshacho ad she'amad b'maneh,
it went down. So I'm stuck, obviously כסף can use the
קנין כסף. נותן מאתים, nosein masayim, הקדש hekdesh stays, they keep the
two hundred. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? ונתן הכסף וקם לו. v'nasan hakessef
v'kam lo. But here's going to be the surprising line.
פדהו במנה. padahu b'maneh. gave
100, ולא הספיק למשוך עד שעמד במאתים, ve-lo hispik limshoch ad she-amad
be-matayim, now it's up to 200. So you might think that הקדש
Hekdesh can say the sale isn't done yet, right? We're going to
use משיכה meshicha, this time. No, here the הלכה halacha is מה
שפדה פדוי, ma she-pada paduy, actually the cash, it's the sale is
binding, ואין עושין לו אלא מנה, ve-ein osin lo ela maneh, and
I and I only have to give 100, I do not have
to give 200. Why? Why can't הקדש Hekdesh say, why can't הקדש
Hekdesh say, we want to be like הדיוט, hedyot, we want to
use משיכה, meshicha we're going to raise the price? אמאי Amai says
the גמרא, הכא נמי נימא לא יהא כוח הדיוט חמור מהקדש? hacha
nami nima lo yehei koach hedyot chamur me-hekdesh? So the גמרא's answer
is אטו הדיוט לאו במי שפרע קאי? atu hedyot lav be-mi she-para
kai? One minute. And even a normal person the הלכה halacha is,
after the cash is given before משיכה, meshicha a normal person who
backs out after the cash is given gets a curse. The curse
is מי שפרע, Mi she-para, basically if the one who exacted punishment
against the דור המבול Dor Ha-mabul and against all these people, that
God should exact punishment against somebody that doesn't stand up to his
commitments. Okay, so basically if I paid cash and now you're backing
out, you're entitled to back out but you're going to get a
curse. Okay, that's the הלכה halacha in בבא מציעא. So therefore, even
when הקדש Hekdesh has the right to use משיכה, meshicha they're not
going to use משיכה meshicha when it is seen as inappropriate as
violating a trust in the הדיוט hedyot context. So they can go
by משיכה meshicha if משיכה meshicha was done and they want משיכה
meshicha, to be final. But if they did כסף, they can't say
we're going to reject כסף and go by משיכה because even a
normal person is not supposed to back out once the כסף has
been paid.
Wait, but did they do משיכה or not?
No, they only did כסף and not משיכה, and that's why they're
not supposed to back out. All
right.
In other words, even though ידו של הקדש על העליונה, yado shel
hekdesh al ha-elyona,
you can't use that to enable the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash to
be scoundrels. They have to stand by their commitment.
Correct. Exactly.